welcome back
you've been exercising to keep yourself
in good shape but from time to time you
need to monitor how you're doing the
body mass index and weight to height
ratios help you check on the state of
your body now in the same way debt to
asset or net worth change ratios are
good indicators of your financial health
money minds ellen lokajaya finds out
more about how to monitor your progress
in the wealth creation aspects of your
financial plan
we exercise to keep ourselves healthy
and fit
and how do we know that we've reached
our health goals some may just weigh
themselves and figure out their body
mass index while some might visit a
doctor to get a health checkup
but how do you go about it when it comes
to financial health
well you can find out if your financial
goals are on track by using financial
ratios to assess the health of your
finances
one financial ratio is called the basic
liquidity ratio the ratio helps you to
find out how much money you have to
cover your expenses in the event of an
emergency
you calculate your ratio by taking your
liquid assets which includes cash and
bank accounts divided by your monthly
expenses like car loans utilities and
groceries
for example if you have thirty thousand
singapore dollars of liquid assets
dividing that by your monthly expenses
of say eight thousand dollars gives you
the ratio of 3.75
the ratio means you have enough liquid
assets to cover your expenses for almost
four months in the event you lose your
job or when faced with an emergency
so how much cash reserves do you think
you should have in the bank
money mine went to the streets to find
out
uh at least 500 right now
uh probably about three months it gives
you like a three-month runway
inside the bank a million dollars
definitely at least six months six
months reserve
so what do the experts say about how
much cash reserves you should have in
the bank
one of the most fundamental objective of
financial planning is to ensure that one
person have enough cash flow in the
event of emergency in the event let's
say you lost your income
with enough liquidity at least you can
have um
time to look for a job like usually you
want to recommend to have about six
months of liquidity um which is six
months of your monthly expenses as your
liquidity ratios so that um let's say in
the event of emergency you have some
ethical time to
to work out the emergency
although holding cash might be safe it
doesn't build wealth
many of my
survey reports
think of that singaporean
holds 33 except in cash
so
it can translate to 33 months of uh
monthly income which is uh
quite a lot a lot more than many
countries you see so to me it's not
healthy because you are not
letting your money work harder for you
you just you should stay invest
imagine
imagine once inflation kicks in your
producing hour is reduced yo that's
where you can see the problem
how do you know if you're holding too
much cash
one of the financial ratios used to
determine that is the liquid assets to
net worth ratio you calculate this by
taking your liquid assets like your cash
and bank accounts divided by your net
worth like your house car and
investments which gives you the liquid
assets to net worth ratio
so if you have 30 000 worth of liquid
assets divided by sale net worth of 200
000 you get 0.15
this means 15 of your net worth is
liquid assets which is the recommended
guideline
a higher number would not be considered
good as liquid assets yield low returns
besides how much cash you have another
important thing to understanding your
financial health rests on how you read
your debt levels
do you know how much debt you have to
your total assets
i don't have much i may be about 10 10
or so i should have zero debt
um
and and just assets know that
but i believe that there are still some
debts right
nope nope so far no dead
no definitely
the least the better 10 estimate zero
depths i mean that's up to me
so how do you calculate your debt to
asset ratio
take your total debt like your credit
card bills car loan and home mortgage
loan divided by your total assets like
your home car and investments which
gives you the debt to asset ratio
so for example if you have debts of four
hundred thousand dollars dividing that
by your total assets of one million
dollars you will get a ratio of 0.4 this
means 40 percent of your financial
status is in debts
so the higher the ratio means that you
have a lower disposable income of course
when during good time all of us can feel
the impact but when it comes to for
example paid cards or financial crisis
that that's where this this ratio really
know where you stand
35 percent below is considered healthy
and 45 percent above is considered
unhealthy
another financial assessment tool that
is familiar to singapore residents is
the total debt service ratio or tdsr
it helps you to understand your ability
to pay off your debts and also lets you
know what percentage of income is left
after paying your debt obligations
to calculate your tdsr take your total
monthly debt repayment divided by your
monthly income to get your ratio
and in this example if you have two
thousand five hundred dollars in monthly
debt repayment dividing that by a
monthly income of four thousand dollars
gives a ratio of 0.63
this means 63 of your monthly income
goes to debt
servicing so um
having a high ratio means that a
person's a big proportion of a person's
income is actually used to pay off um
mandatory actually debts and um
then basically that that
means that um might not be sustainable
over the longer term yeah so usually
what we recommend is to have a ratio of
35 percent and below so that um there'll
be actually more resources for other
let's say household or personal
these financial ratios are just some
simple tools that you can use to check
your financial health and also help you
handle risks and make better investment
decisions to reach your financial goals
to me um it will depends on how well you
plan and execute
at your young age
of course in general perceptions that
you know
the more you're getting older the more
mature you are you're you're more uh
risk adverse or conservative
but to me it's not totally right you
know imagine that some person you know
start saving and pan during the young
younger day
so when when they grow older the the
financial ratio is very healthy and
excellent so which means that he can
take a more risk tolerance compared to a
young person who had poor ratio
and just like ensuring you are on track
with your health goals with yearly
checkups financial planners recommend
that you meet with them at least once a
year to ensure that your financial
health is in shape to reach your
retirement goals
you